[Music]
so
welcome everybody to episode 19 of ask
abhijit i hope you're doing well
today we are discussing geopolitics
so like i've explained before
geopolitics is the
game in which every nation pursues its
national interest on the global scale
on the global stage it's the pursuit of
the national interest and various
advantages like power
influence territory etc on the global
scale and resources as well
and some nations make up the rules some
nations follow the rules the strong
nations make the rules
everybody else follows the rules so
that's how it goes
so it's a pursuit of the national
interest so the national interest is not
some vague
fuzzy undefined term it has a very
specific and clear definition
so let me show you what the national
interest is let me just put it on
this is the national interest
safeguarding and promoting the long term
security prosperity territorial
integrity
self-determination and cultural
of the nation and its people
so this is the national interest it's a
rough definition of the national
interest it is how i define it now every
country has its own idea of the national
interest
for example india doesn't believe in
cultural integrity
india's laws constitution and government
policies
actively undermine cultural integrity
some countries so
believe that their national interest
means conquering the whole world
etc and some countries don't even pursue
that national interest like india for a
very long time in the
after independence did not really pursue
his national interest it gave up so many
advantages that it had
for example it refused to be a permanent
member of the un
security council even though it was
offered this position twice
and much more so every country has its
own way
of either pursuing the national interest
or not pursuing its national interest
but it is the countries that pursue
their national interests the most
vigorously on the global stage that are
the true
world powers and the and the leaders of
the world
so that's all about national interest
and geopolitics
and as always you guys have asked me a
wonderful
question so great deal of questions i
have picked a few of these
so let's get into it right away so aj
asks how can a country have nuclear
weapons
what's the process and how did a country
like pakistan manage to get
nukes good question so first of all
in order to get nuclear weapons a
country needs access to resources such
as raw materials like uranium ore
or thorium which can be converted into
a weapons grade fissile material
so uranium is the most common raw
material that you get
naturally occurring uranium is
uranium-238 it's 99
plus uranium-238 but the weapons the
fissile the
material that is used in weapons is
uranium-235
which is about 0.7 percent of what
occurs naturally
so uranium ore has to be purified and
upgraded
until it becomes weapons-grade uranium
which means it's about 80
plus uranium-235 so first of all a
nation needs
access to the raw material then it needs
the ability to refine uranium and turn
it into weapons-grade uranium
and so that is a complicated
technological process so you need to
develop the technology to do it which is
quite hard
right you need to there are a number of
ways in which you can purify uranium
there are
centrifuges and other methods too so
that's a
that's a big hurdle that one has to
cross one needs
also to have most likely i mean it's
best to have
a civilian nuclear program with nuclear
reactors so you know how to handle these
things
and that also would enable you to create
plutonium
which is also something that is used as
a web
as in nuclear weapons it's another
fissile material
it's uh another fissile element
so you need to be able to obtain either
weapons grid uranium
235 or plutonium then you need to be
able to shape that
you need the you need to know the
technical know-how of how to
assemble a nuclear weapon a nuclear bomb
right so that's actually pretty simple
the nuclear physics is very simple
actually
but the engineering behind it is the
complex part the complicated part
so you need to be able to either
assemble a simple fission device
or a more advanced fission fusion
thermonuclear device
so this is all uh this is all about
engineering it's about
acquiring and perfecting the technology
to do this
and then you need to test it out because
without testing you don't know if your
device works or not
and once you test it you need delivery
systems so if you have a nuke
but you don't know how to deliver it to
your enemy right
then there's no point having a nuke so
you need either to invest in
various missiles other short range or
long range ballistic missiles depending
on where your
adversaries are or you need to have
another kind of delivery method such as
maybe an air force or
aircraft that can go and deploy the
payload and drop the payload
so these are the things these are the
steps this is a very simplified
streamlined
overview of the steps it it takes
for a country to have nuclear weapons
right so
first of all you need to acquire the
weapon then you need to be able to
deliver it
so to acquire the nuclear weapons is the
main thing and how did a
country like pakistan manage to get
nukes well the pakistanis were given the
technology by the chinese
and the delivery systems were given to
the chinese by the north koreans who are
again
basically a proxy of the chinese so the
chinese
intend to use pakistan as a
destabilizing force over india
on the western border and that's why
they have done this that's why they have
proliferated the technology in the 80s
there was some proliferation of
technology from the west as well
there was a scientist called abdul qatar
khan
who acquired blueprints of i think
it was a blueprints of
nuclear reactors i believe from the west
and that's how he was able to establish
this khan research laboratories in
kahuta
etc and that has also enabled the
pakistanis to develop the nuclear
program
so they have been able to develop it
with the help of the west and of
mainly of the chinese so that is the
story in brief
about nuclear weapons and how the
pakistanis acquired them
even the north koreans have to some
extent been
aided by the chinese but it kind of
backfires because
mr kim can also aim to point those nukes
at beijing right
in order to acquire more independence
and autonomy from
from mr xi so that's how it works
okay question number two why isn't china
declaring a war against india being so
powerful
and after how many years are they most
likely to go on a war against
india the highest
form of warfare
is to acquire your military objective
without firing a single shot right
it's what uh what's that movie enter the
dragon that's it's what bruce lee said
it's what bruce lee called fighting
without fighting
so the chinese do not ever want to go to
war with india or with anybody else
they want to acquire the infrastructure
and the military muscle and the
diplomatic
power and every possible means
of acquiring influence and power in
order to
coerce the world into giving it what it
wants
right the chinese never want to go go to
war with anybody and
why do they need to go to war with india
india is doing nothing to threaten the
chinese
india is not developing into a very
rapidly into a very powerful economy
india is not militarizing india is not
going against the one china policy or
whatever it is
india is doing nothing to threaten the
chinese
the chinese are happy they were trying
to uh
do this incursions on the northern
border the india tibet border until last
year
there was this gallowan incident in
which they got a bloody nose
so they have recalibrated their strategy
and over the past
year and a half india has gone backwards
it's gotten it's gone
you know it's uh not progress at all
because of the
situation that we are in right now the
the pandemic
right so the pandemic has achieved
everything china ever would have wanted
to achieve
india's economy has gone backwards
india's space program is stalled
india seems to have just basically
stopped stopped everything
india is not making any progress in any
sense so the chinese are happy why do
they need to go to war
the chinese economy is expanding very
rapidly every
every year including right now during
the pandemic
and the world's economy has stalled
india's economy is also stalled
everything is stopped
so they are doing very well they are
achieving all the objectives they would
ever want to accomplish
right in the short term in the long term
the chinese want india to be fragmented
balkanized and i'm sure they are working
on those things too
india has so many internal divisions
which the chinese do exploit
they do have interests and investments
inside india whether we know it
or not they have investments in the
media they have investments in various
political parties
and in various corporations there are
fdi's there are so many ways
in which the chinese are already
invested in india they're already
pulling at certain strings
etc the chinese don't need to go to war
ever with india
right so that's what india needs to work
on
akash asks what is the polar silk road
and what could be the implications of
the arctic ice melting rapidly for
russia
and for the whole world excellent
question let's take a look at our
our map uh let me put the map on
so this is the globe uh let's zoom in
this here is china
china considers itself to be a near
arctic
nation so the arctic is up north
the arctic circle which is the northern
parts of
of russia of siberia etc so the chinese
consider themselves to be a near arctic
nation
and as the global warming comes into
effect
and as they see all this this region
that we see here
near the arctic circle it's more or less
in in recent memory being permanently
shrouded in ice
it's always ice bound so all of this
blue that you see here the oceans
they're basically unpassable unless you
have an icebreaker
which is a special kind of ship or
unless you have a submarine that to a
nuclear submarine that can be submerged
for
a couple of months or several months at
a time so these passages here
have never really been passable but now
with this global warming coming into
effect the
ice is melting in the arctic region and
this could become an important
waterway for trade and other purposes
so the chinese are already planning
ahead they want to create
infrastructure that allows them to uh
conduct trade
with europe via the arctic sea route
which is
from here if you can see my pointer from
here all the way up there and going
there instead of going to the malacca
straight and all these choke points
which india if it ever wakes up someday
in the future could possibly choke off
so the chinese are looking at exploiting
this route for trade and other purposes
they already have ships that can do this
they have a very large
naval a merchant naval fleet which
serves a dual purpose it is basically a
civilian fleet
which is used for transportation and
maritime merchant activities so they
would like to exploit this
and so that is the implication china
could basically encircle russia
using this methodology right now the
russians
are basically cooperating with the
chinese but it
is definitely something the russians
would be very much very about
about being encircled by the chinese
because at the
to russia south you have a very strong
chinese presence as you can see on the
map right
this here is russia this year is china
mongolia really doesn't matter
it's not a powerful country in any sense
militarily or economically
the chinese can always overrun mongolia
and so the russians feel threatened by
the chinese and if the chinese were to
establish
a permanent uh silk road so to say in
the arctic it could become a bigger
threat for the russians right
so this is all the game of geopolitics
russia and china are quasi allies right
now but
the game is more complex than it appears
at first glance
so these are some of the implications of
the arctic ice melting in the chinese
trying to create
a new trade route the polar silk road
it could affect the eu it could affect
the us it could affect the entire
balance of global power so that is what
china are is
china is contemplating right now that's
what they are vigorously planning for
and they already put taking steps to put
various kinds of infrastructure in into
into position to do this and russia as
of now is cooperating but let's see how
it goes i see them
being very happy about this in the long
run
okay jatin ask asks what role does isro
play in strengthening india at the war
front or at the military level
see any space program always has
a strong military dimension whether it
is stated or unstated
the first application of space is always
in the in the
military realm for example recently
india
a couple of years ago i think uh tested
uh
an anti-satellite uh vehicle
an anti-satellite missile which is a
technology india should have developed
in the early 2010s but it was not
the permission was not given to israel
by the then government
so it's been done now so space always
has
a great deal of uh a great significant
role to play in the military because
space gives you a vantage point
over the entire globe if you have a
network of satellites it can be used for
various purposes india has a number of
remote sensing satellites a large number
of these
now remote sensing is a euphemism for
military satellite because
military satellites do precisely that
remote sensing
they look at the earth and its geography
and its terrain
through various different kinds of kinds
of lenses
so in various spec in various
bands of the electromagnetic spectrum
and all that to to get different kinds
of uh
basically data from the geographical
terrain so
certain satellites are able to peer
through clouds
and nowadays satellites have a very good
resolution like they can
resolve objects that are like one foot
in size
or even smaller maybe even smaller some
satellites may be able to actually read
the time on your watch
if you are if you are standing on the
ground so
that is the thing about satellites they
can give you a lot of data
and information satellites can be used
to coordinate military assets on the
ground or in the ocean
in real time so every military asset
knows whether it's a ship or
a tank or or an infantry division
or any other asset you can coordinate
all of these different assets
in real time to give the commanders
a real time large picture about what's
happening on the battlefield
and across the strategic board
so these are the rules that the military
that the space program plays
in the military front and india does
have naval satellites and other
remote sensing satellites india does
have anti-satellite technology and so
does russia china and the us
and maybe a couple of more countries
perhaps so all of this
does come into play so having a strong
space program is extremely beneficial
for your military
because it gives you a whole different
dimension
to the military chess board so ethro
does play a significant role in
strengthening india at the war
front it is the uh it is the
technologies that isro has developed
that also find
uses in the ballistic missile program
right
so if india needs an icbm the pslv can
serve as an icbm a stop-gap icbm
which can basically deliver payloads
anywhere
on the planet and so on so so it's it's
very useful
and it's very beneficial to have a space
program so i am really thankful that
at least in this field india has taken
the initiative and developed a
reasonably good space
program i would like to see the space
program develop
further and faster i mean india has some
of the best scientists in the world
india has the best scientist in the
world and
i don't see why i don't understand why
isro is not
being allowed to develop more powerful
rockets
why is not allowed being allowed to
develop reusable rockets
right reusable space boosters like
spacex is doing
a private company has gone leaps and
bounds ahead of israel in less than a
decade
spacex right why can't israel do that
with the full funding and support of the
u of the indian government
so i would like to see the indian
leadership to have a little bit more
ambition on the stay in the space
for a field and on the in this domain
because it is
really beneficial for the country and
its national interest in the long run
so i would like to see that happen
akash asks is the russian annexation of
ukraine justified or is it immoral
and injudicious okay so first of all
it's uh
it's not the whole of ukraine that was
annexed it was i think the
the crimean peninsula in the black seed
which was annexed
i think in the early 2010s in 2014 if
i'm not mistaken
i may be off by a year or two that's
fine doesn't matter but it's
in it's the crimean peninsula was which
was
next by russia is it immoral there's
nothing moral or immoral
in geopolitics it's all about the
pursuit of the national interest by any
means necessary
there is no morality in the national
interest it's all
about cold hard calculations and
achieving
your objectives in the best possible way
using the least possible resources is it
in is it
in judicious well did russia suffer any
repercussions
none at all so it's a very good step it
was not injudicious in the least
so let's again look at this matter from
the maps perspective geographical
perspective
so let's go eastward oh sorry westwards
this here is the black sea
and this peninsula here in the center of
the image
is the crimean peninsula as you can see
there is this dashed line here which
google has placed which indicates that
they are not happy with their next
session but it is a defect to annexation
and they can do nothing about it
so here over here to the east if you can
see my pointer this is russian territory
it's russia
this nation here is the ukraine
and crimea was a part of the ukraine and
russia annexed it
so there's a story behind this right so
it
uh so to understand these matters of
geopolitics you actually have to
understand history because there's
always a back story and there's some
context
to anything that happens right now right
everything that happens right now has
some contextual
linkages in the cause and effect chain
that go back
several centuries typically so we have
to go back to the time of the mongol
empire so in the 13th century chinggis
khan emerged out of nowhere
in mongolia and he conquered a vast
territory
which included at the time mongolia
china
and iran and central asia right and
after he died the territory was expanded
by his sons who indulged in pure
conquest they did not do it in
retaliation they just did it for the
sake of conquest
his sons so after chinese khan died his
territory was divided among his sons
and it was his grandson jochi
it was his grandson jochi who was the
who established it wasn't his grandson
joji his son was jochi his grandson was
batu
joche's son so ching is khan's grandson
batu khan
established the so-called golden horde
which was the
north west uh section of the mongol
empire
and that essentially included much of
russia
and eastern europe and the crimea
region was part of it right so after a
couple of centuries about the 15th
century or
somewhere like that when the mongol
empire began to wane
that's when crimea became an independent
khanate a kingdom which was called a
khanate it was called the crimean
khanate
so it was a turkish-sized kingdom a
turkish-sized khanat
an islamic kingdom which was then in the
18th century most likely
annexed by the russian empire
now the russian empire became the ussr
after the russian revolution
in i think 1917 and
so crimea became part of the ussr
as did ukraine now what happened was
that
the ussr assigned this region of crimea
to ukraine at the time ukraine was a
part of the ussr
so crimea was assigned to ukraine for
administrative purposes for the purpose
of administration right
for bureaucratic purposes so ukraine
so crimea became part of the ukraine in
the ussr
inside the ussr this nation now after
the soviet union after the ussr
disintegrated in the early 1990s
all the various republics such as
kazakhstan was biggest
turkmenistan kyrgyzstan tajikistan
ukraine
etc declared their independence and
seceded from this old nation and they
all became independent
nations and what happened was that
ukraine kept crimea
as an independent nation after it
declared its independence so crimea
became part of the independent nation of
ukraine
in the early 1990s and at that time
russia was in a deep recession
russia was very weak it was
disintegrating not the ussr but russia
and you had boris yeltsin in power who
was
well he was not the best leader and
therefore crimea remained
with ukraine as an accident of history
now after boris yeltsin went his way
and vladimir putin came in vladimir
putin quickly reorganized the country
took control
of the country started strengthening it
economically
militarily again etc and
he was always aware of this historical
injustice
that was the uh that was that crimea
remained with the
with ukraine became part of the ukraine
after the disintegration of the ussr
and that's why he always had his eyes on
the crimean peninsula
in 2008 i believe the ukrainians were
complaining about
vladimir putin issuing russian passports
to people who lived in the crimea
and things soon came to a head and in
2014 the russians
basically were put in a next crimea
so for them it is perfectly legitimate
it was always part of the ussr it was
always part of the russian empire and
the russian state the the country of
russia today is the
inheritor of the legacy of the russian
empire and therefore
for him it is perfectly legitimate that
crimea returns to russia
and there's a significant russian
population as well so there is no right
or wrong
they saw this as a historical injustice
and they redressed it
by beings means of taking military
action right
so they have done what they saw is right
what they feel is right
and there is no there is no morality or
immoral
immorality in this it's all about the
balance of power
power will do what power does and that
is the rule of geopolitics there is no
there is no morality or any such thing
in that it's all about
furthering your national interest and
that's what vladimir putin does
relentlessly so that's about
ukraine and the crimea
shriya asks please talk about mao and
his smash
sparrow campaign many chinese communists
are really dumb but the world should
protect itself and wait for them to do
something stupid like smash sparrow
campaign
and cause self-harm so that's an
interesting story
so mao zedong came to power in china
in 1949 if i am
not entirely if i'm correct and
he was in this uh he was trying to
emulate the ussr he wanted to replicate
the kind of industrialization
and the military economic power the uss
ussr had
he he idolized joseph stalin
so in in 1958 he embarked upon the great
leap forward in which he tried to
reconfigure the whole nation and turn
peasants and farmers into in into
industrial workers and all that
and one of the things he embarked upon
in this stage in 1958 the great
leap forward was the eradication of four
pests it was uh
it was the sparrow like you said the fly
the mosquito
and the rat so he asked the people of
his country of china to go after these
pests and destroy them all eradicate
them all
so one of these was the sparrow and the
logic was that the sparrows ate a great
deal of
food grains that were meant for humans
and created
and caused a great deal of loss to the
chinese nation so the chinese peasants
all went after the sparrows they
destroyed sparrow nests they smashed
sparrow eggs
and they basically chased sparrows until
the sparrows got so exhausted they fell
out of the sky and died
so within a couple of years what you
found was that
there was a famine in china a terrible
terrible horrific famine and what
actually happens is that the sparrows
don't just eat some food grains they eat
insects and they eat pests
and when the sparrows disappeared these
pests multiplied and low costs and all
kinds of things
you know multiplied across china and it
it caused devastating
uh destructions of crops and
so china went into a terrible famine
the estimates of the deaths are between
40 million to 80 million
people who died because of mao's stupid
step right and the
the tragic thing is that the chinese
government
had stocks of food grains but they never
released those
and therefore the most horrific things
happened in china
there was widespread cannibalism of the
worst i mean there's no cannibalism of
the worst kind it was just cannibalism
which is the most horrific thing you can
imagine and
an unimaginable amount of suffering this
is something even now the chinese
government is
very reluctant to speak about they have
still not released
the records they have of the time so
yeah so this is what the
the chinese did this is what mao did he
caused the deaths of 40 to
40 to 80 million of his own country
people by
embarking on this stupid smash sparrow
campaign
so will the chinese do something like
this in the future no
they learn from their mistakes unlike
other countries
i do not believe the chinese will ever
do something that stupid again like the
smash spyro campaign
right so nowadays there has been the
resurgence in certain things like that
like
instead of sparrows they're saying kill
cockroaches and all that
which is really not going to have the
same kind of effect the chinese
are a very pragmatic people especially
the chinese communist party they learn
from their mistakes they use
science and data to take the country
forward so i don't see the chinese doing
something stupid like that in the future
but this was a monumental disaster as
far as the chinese are concerned
mao zedong my god that guy was he did
some
terrible things to his own country so
this is one of those
okay so man asks russia today is mainly
run
on money from oil gas and defense
industries
and people say most money are being
stashed by the oligarchs in london and
swiss banks instead of being reinvested
to diversify and benefit the russian
economy
is putin corrupt man or is he really a
nationalist
is russia being slowly hollowed out well
good question
now when you talk about oligarchy the
usa is the biggest oligarchy it is big
tech
and the billionaires or the
trillionaires who run everything there
are no trillionaires yet but
a significant portion of the
value or the money or the wealth in the
u.s
is in the hands of a very very small
number of people
the us is the most unequal country in
the world whether we realize it or not
it's a great place
to live in if you are rich and if you
have a great income
it's a terrible place for the poor you
have no idea of the homelessness and the
misery
that the poor experience in the u.s so
we see the us through rose tinted
glasses because indians tend to do well
there
but it's not a great place for someone
who is not
rich now when it comes to oligarchy yes
russia
is using that model vladimir putin is
using the model
see vladimir putin is very clear about
the fact that he doesn't believe about
believe in democracy it's russia is not
a democracy
it doesn't even pretend to be one it's
just a show
a facade that it puts on you know
as kind of a joke as kind of a taunt to
the world that see
we have this election every few years
and vladimir putin always wins
it it has no pretenses to democracy what
what vladimir putin is doing essentially
is he's re he's resuscitating
the russian empire that's what he is
doing so he's essentially the tsar
of russia the new tsar the same with the
that xi jinping is the emperor of china
right they do not believe in democracy
they do not see that democracy is the
right solution
or the right system for their culture
and i don't see anything wrong with with
that
that approach and the uh imperial
system of russia was always like this a
few
people who run the country right that
tsar and his ministers
and his favored industries who run the
country and deal with
take care of business and very strong
economy and very strong
not economy very strong military so that
is the imperial model of russia and
that's precisely what vladimir putin has
recreated
is russia being hollowed out i don't see
russia being hollowed out
russia is actually increasing in
prosperity compared to where it was in
the 1990s right
it's it's basically arrested the slide
of russia
people used to have long queues for fuel
and food
in the 90s today people are happy are at
least
much happier than before there's always
this
protests for democracy that are
engineered by the west but democracy
is not something that's in the blood or
the dna of the russian people
right they are perfectly happy with an
imperial imperial system
with a tsar system so that's what's
happening
in russia yes some people are getting
really rich
but overall the standards are improving
and the country is more secure than
before
it has a very powerful military it is a
reasonably good economy
if you look at the kind of population
russia has and it's it has stable
borders it is
pursuing its national interests and it
is
well so that's what's happening so uh
he i would say that putin is definitely
a nationalist
and is he corrupt well i don't know what
definition of corrupt to use
but he's very straightforward about what
he's doing
he's quite transparent about and he's
unapologetic about what he's doing
so that's why he's so widely admired
about certain sections of the
of the world right so that's what's
happening under mr putin in russia
aman asks what's your opinion about the
relevance of
organizations like brics and the seo
with all their contradictions and
incoherent objectives so when you have
an organization like the brics or the
seo
it these organizations typically go in a
certain direction
and that direction is determined by
which is the
strongest and most influential country
in this group and in both these
organizations brics or seo
the chinese are the most powerful and
most influential and the richest
and therefore these organizations have a
certain agenda which is to
to further the chinese chinese agendas
and the chinese national interest
now brics is more of a lose
configuration
and it doesn't really have much of much
of a direction in which it is going
there is a brics bank which does some
lending for developing
development work in various countries
etc but it's essentially
going in the direction of china and seo
the shanghai cooperation
organization is basically run by two
countries china and
and russia india is now part of it but
india is basically a junior member india
doesn't really set the agenda
so when you have organizations like
these it's always the heavyweights who
set the agenda
and take the organization in a certain
direction the overall objective of these
organizations is always to further the
agenda
and national interest of the predominant
member
or members and that is what we see right
so that's why india had something called
sark but it never never took off because
china because pakistan is a member of
sark and pakistan was always
sabotaging what india was doing and
india always kept pakistan as an equal
and now basically india seems to have
abandoned the entire idea of sark
india should look into creating uh
uh indian ocean region alliance of some
of some sort
but first of all india needs to become
more powerful economically and
militarily and then it can do
and then it can think of think along
these lines
so essentially to answer your question
in brief it's all about the relevance is
that they further the agenda
and the national interest of the most
powerful countries
within these organizations so that's
what brics and seo
whether they whether the objective the
the foundational objective is that or
not
eventually it's always that this is what
keeps this is what
ends up happening it furthers the
national interest and agenda
of the most powerful country or
countries within the organization
okay papa boy what's my view
on russia as a geopolitical ally
russia is an interesting
nation very interesting from our
perspective from india
in the past india was a satellite state
of the ussr india dependent
depended on the ussr for handouts and
technology
and various things and and support on
the industry on the on the international
stage
etc today these are two different
uh policies and two different
world views to some extent right russia
and india
russia has its own agenda and its own uh
own objectives on the global stage india
seems to have its own
national interest which differs to some
extent from what the russians want
right india basically as of today
doesn't see itself as a big geopolitical
player
india seems india seeks stability and
security in the
in the near abroad of india so that's
all that india is
seeking right now and india obviously
has a
big problem with china the expansionist
hegemonic
rise of china which threatens india to a
great deal and it also threatens russia
to a great deal
so the thing is india and russia still
do have a great deal of trust because of
the shared history
and there are shared well the shared
history goes back
not much beyond the ussr and there's a
great deal of
cultural resonance between india and
russia so there is
even though russia and india are no
longer explicit geopolitical allies
there is a great deal of warmth to some
extent now i said i
i did say that they that warmth and
ethics and all that have no place in
geopolitics
but they do smooth things over when
things when there are
then there is some friction and all that
and i always say that
russia and india the geopolitical
interests ally
to the extent that both see china as a
big threat
now this may seem strange because russia
is allying to some extent with china
right now
on the economic front in the military
front also to some extent doing joint
military exercises and they vote
along similar lines in the u in the u n
etc
so there seems to be a kind of alliance
between russia and china but
as you know as i've said before the
russians have also pointed nuclear
missiles at the chinese
right even at the chinese the russian
chinese border
so you have this border here where are
we
so this here is china this here is
russia this enormous country
and there is a shared border to the east
right over here this is the shared
border and there is another shared
border a small 50 kilometer stretch
over here between mongolia and
the nation of kazakhstan so the russians
have deployed batteries of
iskandar nuclear missiles ballistic
missiles
at various points along the border
and the russians also have long range
ballistic missiles pointed at various
parts
in china including especially beijing
and i can imagine that the chinese would
also have returned the favor returned
the favor and pointed missiles
at moscow so even though these two
countries appear to be geopolitical
allies
they are actually long-term adversaries
they have almost gone to war in the past
the ussr almost decided to nuke china
in the 1960s so they have a very fraught
relationship in the past and it's not
going to get so better anytime soon
because the russians because the chinese
have designs on siberian territory
and they see it as an unfinished agenda
so
the russians don't trust the chinese the
least
when it comes to trust they trust india
much more than that then they see india
as a more reliable
long-term partner if not an ally
and that's why we see that the russians
are selling the s-400 missile system
to india as well as to china right so
they have sold it to china first but
then they
they're selling it to india as well to
counter balance china
so russia is an interesting nation i
think india and russia will
continue to have a good long-term
relationship it all depends on
how china behaves and how the india u.s
relationship goes
the russians are not happy about the
indians getting closer to the us
but that's inevitable because of the
geopolitical situation vis-a-vis china
but i think over the long term india and
russia will have a good relationship
and depending on how the u.s how the
russia-china relationship goes
india and russia could even get closer
in the future depending on
various factors such as these so it's
complicated but
overall it's a good relationship and it
could become stronger in the future
geopolitically maybe even an alliance
someday
anirudh asks china is a powerhouse of
global trade and heavily relies on
shipping routes across the indian ocean
that requires passage to the malacca
strait why can't india take
it as a serious opportunity much more
than right now to strongly militarize
and build secure naval bases at the adam
and nicobar islands which lie at the
straits mouth
eventually even making it possible to
completely block their trade via this
route okay let me show the map once
again
so this here is the map and the malacca
route the malacca straits are here
so this is a narrow choke point the
malacca strait as you can see here
which connects the indian ocean region
to the south china sea the so-called
south china sea
and this is the the route by which all
trade happens between the west and china
all shipping has to pass through the
malacca
strait right so that
is a significant choke point and india
has this
natural advantage of having the andaman
nandikova island chain
over here this is the south most island
over here right
so if india were to militarize these
islands and create naval bases
and other military infrastructure here
it would be a piece of cake if india had
a strong navy
to interdict naval passage through the
malacca strait at
will and that could have very
significant
repercussions on the chinese economy and
on the chinese navy
right so one could block access for the
chinese navy as well
and one could block trade access for
china
so that is one choke point the other one
is over here
the strait of djibouti there's another
one over here
the persian gulf the strait over here
so there are these stroke points that
india has access to
india can utilize them if india has a
strong blue water navy
so the question is why isn't india doing
that oh well i don't know why india
isn't doing that india should do it
india could create these bubbles you
know a280 bubbles
which can interdict any kind of movement
through these regions
aircraft movement or or naval movement
or submarine movements
so if in the future india develops a
blue water navy india would have a
very very significant geopolitical
advantage india would become a global
geopolitical player
just by creating a powerful blue water
navy
and controlling the entire indian ocean
region it's easy for india to do it
all india has to do is to invest heavily
in the navy over the next 10
15 years and develop a large number of
ships of various kinds and sizes the
main thing about a navy is how many
missile
missiles it can carry on a given day how
many missiles can it
deploy at sea on any given day so it is
not about the number of ships you have
it's about the number of missiles you
can deploy
and how well you can deploy these
missiles which means what is the kind of
distributed lethality you have is your
lethality distributed or is it
concentrated
an aircraft carrier is concentrated
lethality missile both small missile
boats large numbers
is distributed lethality so india needs
to think about this very seriously i
think india has a heaven-sent
opportunity
to become the custodian of the seas like
it always keeps saying india's
ministry of foreign affairs keeps on
saying this slogan
that the indian ocean region is our
strategic backyard
but india does nothing to actually act
upon it right
so i hope that someday in the future
soon
india's leadership will develop the
ambition
and the vision to make india stronger
and to further india's national
interests in the long run
by investing strongly in the navy
because india's land routes are cut off
right now
everywhere india has no access to either
asia or to europe because
everything is cut off via pakistan and
and china
so the heaven-sent opportunity for india
is the sea
india should become a strong a powerful
maritime nation
i would say that india should become one
of the top three maritime nations
so i hope that it happens and it's
possible all the things are there you
can see it in the geographical
uh you can see it in the map it's all
possible as long
the only thing india has to do is invest
in a navy so i hope it is done
soon
okay omkar asks do you think the
decision by pakistan to gift
the shaq's gum valley of bill of gilget
balthasan
is a cunning strategy of involving a
third party in the kashmir dispute
eventually making it difficult to
receive to resolve
and india and if india takes back pok in
the future how can we deal with china on
the shaksam valley
let's go back to the map let me show you
where this is so
this is the map here
so as you can see google has placed
these dotted lines to indicate that
these are territories that india doesn't
hold or in that india should not be
holding or something like that
so the saks gum valley is basically here
this here
this place here this northern region so
some part of it has been
ceded by pakistan to china it is part of
pok but now it has become
cojk china occupied jama kashmir
including aksai chin as well
so this northern region if you can see
my mouse pointer here
this is roughly the saks gum valley area
which
the pakistanis have gifted to china in
order to complicate
the jammu and kashmir issue
so yes it does complicate the matter if
india were to
regain pok through military means then
shucks gum valley will remove
remain an outstanding dispute
so how can we deal with china and the
shaksam valley well the
we have to take a long term approach
right
uh it is not being gonna be possible for
india to take back pok unless the tibet
issue is resolved and unless tibet gains
it free its freedom
if that happens then china will be cut
off from pakistan
in which case india will be able to deal
with pakistan
in a separate manner so that's what
needs to happen
china has complicated matters pakistan
has complicated matters by
ceding this territory to the chinese
so yeah it's a cunning ploy it's a very
good play actually if you look at it
from a cold
rationalist perspective
okay abhishek asks would you consider
the achievements of the indians abroad
such as indian origin big tech ceos
political figures like kamala harris
as a contributing factor for increasing
indian influence and positions of power
in international forums
okay so we know that mr sundar pichai is
the
boss of google mr satya nadella is the
boss of microsoft and
various other people are in positions of
power how does it further
india's interests does it further
india's interests
let's go back to the map this
is the google map right google is run by
mr sundar pichai
let's go here to northern india
this is aksai chin which is held by the
chinese
correct let me turn this off for a
second
let me click over here and see what it
says it says unavailable
it says that this region is disputed
let's click here
near gilgit it says unavailable it
doesn't say india it says unavailable
let's go to srinagar and click here it
just gives some number it doesn't say
it's part of india
right over here let's try it again some
number
let's go near nepal this is the india
nepal boundary yes
let's click near the indian enable
boundary over here
okay it says uttar pradesh here sure all
right there are places even near the
india nepal boundary
where it doesn't say india let's go here
and see what happens let's click here
it says nepal even though it's on the
indian side of the border
can you see this it says india here but
if you click there
it says nepal on the indian side of the
border
or in indian territory so this is mr
sundar pichai's google
does it seem to have increased india's
influence anywhere
it hasn't so when your people
work for a foreign country and become
foreign citizens it doesn't really
uh increase your influence
unless you're like china and you use
them as double agents and all that right
so india doesn't play the geopolitical
game india doesn't
use this as leverage india has so many
indians
in the us who work in the u.s and
contribute to the u.s economy
and contribute to the u.s national
interest
china also has a number of chinese
citizens great number of chinese origin
people in the u.s
and many of them work on behalf of the
chinese communist party they have become
double agents
india simply doesn't play this game
right i mean india has much more
leverage than china in the u.s
if you look at these people like mr
sundar pichai satyanath
who's now vice president et cetera
kamala harris is very much anti-india
fyi despite being
a partial indian origin so it's all
about how you play the game whether you
seek influence or not whether you build
influence networks or not
you have to influence you have to you
have to invest
in influence networks you have to
influence you have to invest in power
networks
you have to invest in people and you
have to play this game of influence
india simply doesn't play this game
india is not able to control people
within its own borders
right there are so many uh so-called
anti-national elements in india who
actually advocate the national interests
of other countries
so india's government needs to
i don't know change the way it plays the
game or
or start playing the geopolitical game
because there is so much that india can
achieve
by leveraging the prominent people and
other non-prominent people that india
has all across the world
you go to any country in the world
you'll find indians there any country in
the world
you'll find lots of indians there
especially developed countries western
countries
right india i mean australia new zealand
the western world anywhere
you're gonna run into indians anywhere
on the street if you go there
any country if you go to london it feels
like you're in india essentially right
there are so many indians there and the
same goes for new york and all the major
cities in the u.s
so india should learn how to leverage
this this opportunity that it has
right the same with the chinese do the
same with israelis do across the world
so they said this is a great deal that
india can quickly achieve
if it were to leverage that right now
all that happens is that these people
they serve the national interests of the
countries they live in that's all
so as you can see with google despite
google's boss being an
indian or at least of indian origin it
essentially goes against india's
national interest and
and and shows indian territory as part
of nepal
or as disputed territory right it's just
one example of money
so as of now it doesn't really help
india in any way whatsoever
how big of a role akash asks how big of
a role does religion or culture play in
determining the geopolitical stance of a
country
for example india acts neutral most of
the time is it because of india's
culture or lack of political will
well india's culture has never been
neutral india's culture has always been
look out look abroad go out go outside
etc
india's history shows that we have
always expanded outwards and gone to
various parts of the world
and even settled there even the past
2000 years we had the cholas and the
kaneshka and various
various emperors of india and
national leaders who had this
forward-looking policy
so india has historically never been a
neutral country india has historically
been
a net exporter of influence and culture
and power
india has also conquered territories far
beyond its borders right
so historically india has not been like
this it's not india's culture
india's culture is liberal and diverse
and plural and tolerant and respectful
but it is not timid india's culture has
never been timid
but it's it's since 1947 that india has
acted like this so culture does play a
significant role in the geopolitical
stance of a country
russia has a certain culture and it
plays a certain kind of geopolitical
game
the chinese have a certain culture they
play a certain kind of geopolitical game
the same goes for middle eastern
countries the same goes for european
or western countries or the anglo-saxon
countries the the five eyes countries
the us uk australia new zealand and
canada
and the latin countries as well etc so
every culture
has a certain style of playing
geopolitics and that's what you see
well india also has its style but right
now what we are seeing is a very
different style it's a
it's a post-independence naruvian style
of geopolitics right so that's what we
have seen since
independence so it's basically this
indian neutral game that india stays
neutral and everything india has no
opinion
and will play no part in world affairs
it's a lack of political will nothing
else it's a lack of confidence among the
leadership
so it's all about it's all about the
kind of leadership that india is able to
find
right now the political system is such
that only a certain kind of leader
is allowed to emerge right there's
plenty of leadership potential in this
country plenty of greatness
but that greatness is such that it
disdains the political system which is
so dirty
and therefore it never it is never able
to come to
to power and if a certain kind of person
does go through the political system
over the years they make a lot of
compromises and they become a different
kind of person
and then again you have the same style
of leadership that emerges again
so i i'm not saying every leader is like
that
in recent times we have had much better
leaders as you know
but overall it's about confidence it's
about
developing india into a powerful country
that also builds their confidence and
and changes their outlook
so india needs to become a powerful
economy india is not a powerful economy
right now
and it india needs to become powerful
military which will take some political
will
so essentially it's about india's status
as a country on the geopolitical stage
india doesn't see
itself i mean india's leadership doesn't
see india as a powerful country
or is a big player see when the chinese
were an impoverished nation they had
global leadership aspirations
in the 1970s onwards during mao zedong's
time he wanted to be a global leader
when china was in the throes of
incredible famines and in
misery and poverty right so china has
always
aspired to global leadership position if
even when its gdp was down in the dumps
so it's all about your ambition it's all
about your outlook
it's the about the confidence that your
leaders have so that is what india needs
it's nothing to do with india's culture
india's culture has always been forward
looking
outward looking and it's always been an
extremely confident culture
it's about the leadership that this
current political system
is throwing out it is designed to give
us
a certain kind of leader so that's what
needs to change india needs to change
its political system
somehow now the current political
leadership is invested in the political
culture of india and they don't want it
to change
because it's what brought them to power
india's politicians want things to stay
the same
india's bureaucrats want things to stay
india's institutions want things to stay
the same because these are self-serving
institutions
to a large extent unfortunately i'm not
saying everybody is bad
there are many good people within the
indian system but they are unable to
effect the change because of the inertia
of the system and because the system is
devised in a certain way
so india needs a solution to this
reforms significant
strong reforms right revolutionary
reforms
only that can change india so let's see
how that goes
okay black tiger asks will we ever be
able to take back
our punjabs and the pok is if yes then
how
yes we will be able to take it back it
won't happen tomorrow
it won't happen over the next five years
it can happen in the next 20 years
so it's like this see to reach the moon
you must aim at the stars therefore to
take back
our territories you have to aim further
so essentially the solution to the
pakistan problem the pakista the
solution to the pok punjab sindh
etc problem lies elsewhere it lies
in tibet what india needs to
aim for over the next 20 to 30 years
is to ensure the liberation of tibet
from chinese occupation that would also
have the effect of of
causing the disintegration of the
communist party in china
because no chinese empire can withstand
such a setback
so india needs to slowly steadily
assiduously work towards
freeing tibet from china over the next
20 or 30 years the moment that happens
the punjab sindh pok problem will be
solved automatically
because pakistan will lose its major
supporter and it will crumble pakistan
can also be made to crumble that way
so india needs to think big india needs
to stop looking
at pok india needs to look beyond the
pok
that is the way to achieve geopolitical
objectives
india basically should aspire to become
a global power that one of the top two
or top three powers in the next 20 or 30
years
that's the only way this these things
will be solved the moment you become
that powerful
all of your local near near abroad
problems they resolve themselves on
their own
so that is the solution that's what
india needs to work towards
india needs to expand rapidly
economically
militarily in the sense of influence and
power and all that and then if you if
india does that
all these objectives will be achieved
aman asks what are the reasons behind
the phenomenon of wolf warrior diplomacy
being pursued
by china in the recent years
that's a good question so this wolf
warrior diplomacy is essentially
a more vigorous and
more more assertive diplomacy that the
chinese have been pursuing under
the leadership of mr xi jinping
so traditionally the chinese have had a
very different style of diplomacy
right they had a leader called deng
xiaoping who basically
uh rescued china from the ravages of the
mao mao era
and he brought china back to normalcy
and then he started making china a more
powerful country
and he had this principle tau guang yang
hui
which means keep a low profile bide your
time
while also getting something
accomplished so he
wanted china to work quietly steadily
towards his objectives
was of building a more more powerful
economy in a more powerful military
and building diplomatic uh a powerful
diplomacy diplomatic system etc
while keeping a low profile so during mr
deng xiaoping's time the chinese
diplomats
would basically uh they would
avoid controversy and they used to use
cooperative cooperative rhetoric and
cooperative language
with everybody else right so they were
very polite they were very self-effacing
and that was the kind of approach the
chinese diplomats had
now under mr xi jinping china has a very
different
approach towards everything so mr xi
jinping believes that china's time has
come now
he's advocating his country people
to have four confidences four
confidences this is the approach he's
advocating he's saying the chinese
people
should have the con confidence in their
chosen path
the chosen part of the chinese communist
party they should have confidence in the
political system of the chinese
communist party
they should have confidence in the
guiding theories of the chinese
communist party
and they should have confidence in the
chinese culture
these are the four confidences so now
china has become
is becoming an increasingly strident and
nationalistic country and the diplomats
have totally changed
their approach they are now very happy
to court controversial they are actively
quoting courting controversy
on on various media twitter facebook not
facebook twitter mostly
and in the statements they make and they
are now using
very controver confrontational and
aggressive
rhetoric in their statements so this is
the new approach
of the chinese diplomats and this is
what is now being termed as
wolf warrior diplomacy so this coincide
coincidence coincides with china's
so-called
rise china is much more confident now
it is a much more assertive nation and
it is not afraid
to make strong statements and and take
a confrontational attitude in its
diplomacy
so that is essentially the so-called
wolf warrior diplomacy it is named after
after a couple of chinese movies so
this is a good question
kosub asks does india hold any land in
antarctica like a couple of other
nations
in future what are the advantages of
capturing land there
minerals resources navy etc let's take a
look
at antarctica let me remove the comment
first
okay so antarctica is right to the south
of india
there is nothing between india and
antarctica you just go south you'll
reach antarctica
this here is antarctica the south pole
region and this continent here
so india does have some holdings in the
it's not holdings
india does have three research stations
i believe three of them
in antarctica where it does research
scientific research so india as of now
right now as we speak has about
30 or 40 scientific personnel deployed
in these research stations where various
kinds of scientific research is being
done
now there are i think seven or eight or
nine nations that have territorial
claims to antarctica
but these claims are not being pursued
in any way there is a so-called
antarctic treaty that everybody
that these various nations have signed
including india and china
which prohibits any action or any
exploitation of the resources of
antarctica
so antarctica does have resources
minerals etc
but as of today it is economically
unviable or unfeasible to extract them
because of the because it's so far first
of all fall
from every other place and because it is
ice bound so it's very difficult to mine
these things but as global warming
happens and all that so
it may become viable economically in the
future to do mining there
so yes many countries have interests in
antarctica
chile is one country which has laid
claims to antarctica that the french
have claims in antarctica strangely
enough
and some other countries i think the u.s
has it as well
so the chileans have research stations
here they have about 450 personnel
deployed there the americans have over a
thousand scientists and other personnel
in antarctica the chinese have five
stations five research stations
and they have about 200 personnel in
antarctica
i think they have four research stations
and the fifth one is being constructed
as we speak
so there is uh this preparation going on
among all these various world powers for
a future
push towards antarctica so india does
have three research stations and india
does have
a more or less round the year presence
in antarctica
but as of now as of today the antarctica
region is not being used
or exploited economically in any way but
in the future the
the cards are always on the table it may
definitely happen
in the future so yeah india is uh sorry
so yeah india does have some
uh nominal holdings in antarctica but
india doesn't have any territorial
claims there
unlike various other nations so in the
future antarctica will
maybe be viable if global warming makes
it possible
anirudh asks there have been a couple of
dozen mysterious deaths of israel
scientists over the past few decades
including vikram sarabhais and also an
episode of having nambi narayan
narayanan charged with false espionage
do you think there's a strong foreign
hand involved in all these cases
having tried hindering our space
research program
well there was dr homi baba who died in
a plane crash a mysterious plane crash
in the french in the swiss alps i
believe
i think in the 1960s or yeah probably
1960s
so yes there have been many deaths of
scientists indian scientists
and there is definitely a foreign hand
that seeks
to stop india's progress in the fields
of science and technology
whether it is space science or the
nuclear sciences etc
it's always there there are the global
powers don't want a new global power to
emerge
and india has immense potential the
whole world knows it
india hasn't achieved its own potential
because of various factors
mostly its own internal problems right
india system
is a system of mediocrity it it
ri it raises people it raises mediocre
people to the top
unfortunately whether the education
system or the political system
mostly not always mostly there are
always exceptions
but mostly that's the kind of system we
have so india has been self-sabotaging
itself because of its system
but also there is the foreign hand
various global powers
you can guess who they are who have been
trying to prevent india from
acquiring various technologies or
developing various technologies
you are the u.s sanctions in the wake of
the indian nuclear tests in 98
you had the u.s sanctions on the india
space program
where india was trying to acquire
cryogenic technology from the russians
the americans stopped that because
russia was a very weak country at the
time
in the late 90s so yes the americans
have been involved in this the chinese
have very much been involved in this and
some other countries may also possibly
be involved in trying to sabotage
india's scientific advancement so yes
these
these episodes and occurrences that you
speak about are definitely
there is definitely an element of
foreign interference in this
so yeah i agree it's there it will
continue to be there unless india takes
certain specific
actions
srivanch asks what was the impact of the
chernobyl nuclear disaster on the
geopolitical scene
was it a major reason for the resolution
of the soviet union
and how did this impact the world so it
was not
one of the major factors that caused the
dissolution
of the ussr but it had a significant
impact on
the confidence that mikhail gorbachev
had on the soviet
uh nuclear industry and on soviet
scientists
it became clear that they were basically
not following the best practices
and the various programs were
basically there there were great deals
of inefficiencies and and bureaucratic
bungling
and the thing was not very well run so
mikhail got much of lost confidence
in the this process in the soviet
scientific system
the world also began to see the ussr in
a different light
it was not seen as this it stopped
seeing the ussr as it's all powerful
technologically advanced nation
and basically it had a very bad
effect on the image of the ussr in the
world
and so there was a secondary kind of
effect on the
eventual dissolution of the ussr i do
not see it as a primary cause
of the dissolution or the disintegration
of the ussr
but yes it did have some effect
okay one more question does india have
a vision for where it will be after 100
years of independence just like the
chinese have it
well i don't know if the indian
leadership has a vision for that because
we don't know who's going to be in power
in 2047. india doesn't have a stable
political system
anything can happen at any time a new
political party comes to power and they
will reverse
all the policies of the previous
political
system or the party that's what we've
seen time and again and again
and sometimes when you have these
coalition governments that come to power
for three months or five months
they they basically put in disastrous
policies like what ike gujaral did
he basically exposed all the indian
intelligence
assets in pakistan even moraji decided
that these were people who came to power
because of
coalition politics so india's political
system isn't stable
right and therefore the political
leaders they only have a vision for what
they want to achieve in their own
political party
and when you have a strong leader like
right what we have right now
even their tenure is not certain
right i mean who knows what's going to
happen in the next election
one hopes it continues but we don't know
so the political system isn't stable it
doesn't give you a great deal of
certainty in the long run
and therefore this system ensures that
india's leadership
doesn't have a long-term vision
of where india wants to be i am sure
some leaders have a long-term vision of
where india wants to be
but that vision isn't certain right
because of the
vagaries of the indian political system
in the case of china
the chinese communist party will most
likely be there until
2049 when it will be 100 years of their
independence
of the of the coming to power of the
chinese communist party so
they have political continuity they have
a continuity of policies and all that
and therefore they are able to build a
vision they are able to have a vision
and work towards that in the case of
india's so-called democratic
chaotic system it's very hard to work
towards a vision
election after election but
india should have a vision of where it
wants to be india should
in 2047 be at least a 20 trillion dollar
economy
india should have a full-fledged space
program
india should have people on the moon
hopefully people on mars as well
india should have a proper blue water
navy
india should have resolved the tibet
issue and the pok issue and the pakistan
issue
and the afghanistan issue right india
should be
in my opinion that one of the top two
countries in the world by 20 2047 that
should be india's vision
india's living standards should be way
ahead of where they are today
right india's per capita gdp should put
the
it in the middle income nations at least
right india should have revamped its
education system
and become much more confident
culturally than what it is today
so these are some of the things that
india should aspire to and that's the
kind of vision india should have
but will india's political system allow
that we don't know
i hope it does so that's the kind of
vision india should have
in my personal opinion
okay right let me take a few live
comments
live chat comments
good question by kunal
where does india rank in cyber warfare
well these capabilities if india does
have them will not be publicized
so as of now we don't know i hope india
is working on that
i hope it is india has the best i.t
talent in the world india has the best
scientific minds in the world
so india should rank well in cyber
warfare
maybe you should not demonstrate your
capabilities unless you have to until
you have to
but as of now we don't know where india
ranks in this when it comes to super
computing
india is not a major super computing
nation
right india doesn't have the best super
computers among the top 100 super
computers india may have maybe
two or three super computers perhaps
when it comes to
machine learning artificial intelligence
india hasn't made many
too many strides when it comes to
quantum computing it's not even taken
off in
in india so the signs aren't very good
but
hopefully we are doing something maybe
behind the scenes
so i hope india is doing well but as of
now we don't know india's
capabilities at at first
at first glance india doesn't seem to
have very strong
capabilities when it comes to cyber
warfare but i hope
i hope i am wrong
aditya asks why can't we embrace one
world instead of embracing nationality
i would like to but will the world allow
me to i mean
yeah people talk about this this is a
very idealistic moralistic
position to take i am not criticizing
you this is a good position to take
in an ideal world you would want to have
one world
with lots of different local cultures
and no borders no visas no passports
right but that's not how the world works
the world works in a very different way
in the west we have this globalism right
now this which is now
now a big big thing that's in that's in
the west
and they talk about having no borders
and and the world is one and we should
adopt our culture and we should adopt
our values
but hey have they abolished passports
have they abolished visas
no they are strengthening passports and
visas and national borders
so it's not practical to
to have one world instead of embracing
nationality right
every country is pursuing its national
interest when that happens you
have to embrace nationality right
so this is an idealistic position it's
great if this was to happen
but it's never going to happen not
within our lifetimes
okay money says i think it was the
british who gave the cocoa islands to
burma and the burmese who gave it to
china okay let's talk about the cocoa
islands
so the cocoa islands are the
northernmost islands in the andaman
nicobar chain
these are the cocoa islands it wasn't
the british who gifted the cocoa islands
to burma sir
it was our great prime minister sri
jawal nehru
who did that and if we look at
the cocoa island here let me put on the
satellite mode
right so as you can see there is this
extensive infrastructure here there is
this airstrip cocoa island airport
and there is all this infrastructure
that you see here very well developed
there are lots of facilities here
it's very well planned very well
developed etc this is not burmese these
are not burmese facilities
these are chinese facilities
so the burmese junta hunter whatever you
call it
they gifted it they handed it over this
asset
to the chinese so it was our great prime
minister
nehru who gave it to the burmese and it
was the burmese who
have basically handed it over to the
chinese and the chinese have these
this scientific station here it's a
signal station
it is basically used to listen to
various kinds of signals
and basically spy on indian activities
in the andaman endicover
islands so it's a very important
asset for the chinese it gives them a
very good idea of what's happening in
this region
because they have a great deal of
interest in this region especially
because of the malacca
choke point so that is the situation it
wasn't the british who gave it it was
our great prime minister shari
jawaharlal nehru
what do i think about bhutan i think
it's a great country sir if you have a
specific question you can ask me
okay some more questions
abhishek asks should india reoccupy the
cocoa islands
would it be a great geopolitical move
given the coup and the china using the
islands for military base
well that would be an act of war against
burma and china both
the question is sure it's a great move
to take back the islands
does india have the strength to take
them back and retain them
will there be any repercussions you have
to see the overall
effect of such a move you have to do a
proper war gaming scenario
in which you take into account all the
effects
second-order effects all the
repercussions right
so i think india is not strong enough
economically and militarily especially
from a naval viewpoint
to do this at this time right it would
be construed as
an act of territorial aggression and it
would basically legitimize any other
territorial aggression that china would
take after this so india has to consider
all of this in the big picture context
and only then take a decision
as of today in my opinion india cannot
india should not do it
until it has a proper blue water navy
that can
withstand any kind of threat from the
chinese right
so as of now it's not really possible
okay let me take a couple of more
questions
geetham asks if war broke out in the
south china sea will china invade taiwan
will japan korea vietnam and the
philippines alive with the us for war
will india be pulled into this war
also can india take advantage so i
believe that uh
the south china sea issue is here let's
see
so this is the bone of contention taiwan
it's an independent country uh india
doesn't seem to recognize it as an
independent country
india doesn't have diplomatic ties with
taiwan and china
regards taiwan as a renegade province so
china says that taiwan is very much a
part of china and it will be reunified
in due course of time
and this is the number one target for
china in the short to medium term
i believe china will take over taiwan
taiwan in the next five to ten years
as its military and economic strength
increases its naval strength increases
and as the united states declines which
is happening as we speak
so i believe that the chinese will take
over taiwan within the next five to ten
years they will at least make a move to
do it
make a move whether the u.s tries to
stop them or not is to be seen
china will do it only when they are
completely sure that the u.s will not be
in a position
to fight back so this is
in my opinion a matter of time will
japan korea vietnam and the philippines
alive with the us for war
my my real question is will the u.s even
have the appetite for war
right so i think it's doubtful
i think the chinese will make this move
only when they are
100 confident that the u.s is no longer
in a position
to try and stop them and
when this happens then the chinese navy
will be
free to move into the indian ocean
because this threat is over
so that is the big issue for india if
slash when the chinese take over taiwan
they will make
a concerted effort to become the
major indian ocean region power which is
why i keep saying that india needs to
act proactively
and build a blue water navy right now
when it has the time
okay one final question one final
question for today
okay what do i think about lakshadweep
why does india not have a grip
on this land so that the lakshadweep
islands are north of the maldives
they are on east india's western
coast of india's western coast all of
these islands here
off the coast of kerala india basically
well it's it's our territory of course
india
does own this territory but india has
basically lost
some kind of cultural control over this
territory you could say right
so like the lakshmi have essentially
become
become kind of culturally like the
maldives
and now they are demanding cultural
autonomy of sorts
which is being aided and embedded by
certain political parties in india
so this is a strategically important
region in my opinion india should
develop some of these islands
create some artificial islands if
necessary like the chinese have done
in the south china sea and build proper
naval bases here
so india should do this it's a very
important strategic
asset and resource for india it is
something that is waiting to be
developed it can be
invaluable it can become another
unsinkable aircraft carrier
like the luxury like the andaman and
koba islands already are potentially so
i think
india should develop
these islands as naval and military
bases and some of these can also be used
for tourism
and all that right so whatever is
happening right now on the political
domain needs to be resolved quickly
this sort of behavior cannot be uh
cannot be allowed right when people try
to
demand a separate set of rules for
a certain territory which is part of
india so that's what needs to be done my
friends
uh well i think we are done for today
thank you very much for all of your
wonderful
very interesting questions we will
continue doing this but for today
it is the end of this episode so thank
you for watching so much for watching